So this is interesting because we can have
a nice theorem which says that, so this particular
form of UCB is actually called UCB 1 right,
and in the literature if you generally see
UCB without any qualifier assigned to it,
it usually means UCB1 okay, there are many
many variants on it we are not going to look
at all the variants there is like normal UCB
then UCB Revisited, UCB Improved, UCB2 right
so, there are many many variations of UCB
right and each one gives you a slightly better
theoretical results than the one that I am
going to write down right, and sometimes involving
exponentially harder analysis.
UCB1 is fairly trivial compared to the other
algorithms that were proposed later and I
just want to give you a flavor of the kind
of work that is done in this area right, so
I am NOT going to get into the other things
but we will certainly put all those papers
up on Moodle, if people want to read they
can read those okay. Another thing about UCB1
is that we can have arbitrary reward distributions
so, some of the other algorithms that are
out there assume say Bernoulli rewards right
for showing their results and so on so forth
the right thing about UCB 1 is arbitrary reward.
So capital delta i is Q star a star minus
Q star i essentially this means the loss that
you will incur if you play i, the expected
loss that you will incur if you play i instead
of playing a star, right you remember what
a star is, the max over a of Q star a right
so, that is a star, argmax a of Q star a is
a star right so I will always denote by a
star the optimal action right so, what does
this tell you, so the regret right is upper
bounded by eight times ln n by delta I, the
summation running over all the non optimal
arms ,why all the non optimal arms? Because
delta I is 0 for optimal arm, so I do not
really want that to figure in the summation
okay, plus 1 plus pi squared by 3 that is
the magic constant okay, times summation over
all j delta j right.
And here i am being little sloppy i have to
exclude the optimal arm here also but i do
not because it is 0 anyway, delta j 0 anyway
so, I mean symmetrically just as I have this
summation here I should have the summation
there, but I can be a little sloppy and I
can write it like that because, i do not have
to worry about the additional 0 terms I'm
adding okay, great. How did we get from here
to there or more importantly how do we get
this expression? Right so before we go on
so I want to introduce a little bit of notation
here
that's the term that tells you the number
of times it is a random variable that represents
the number of times I have played arm i in
the first n trials okay.
Number of times I have played arm i in the
first n trials does it make sense, so then
i can write my regret after n trials as summation
over i expected value of that times delta
i, people get that so the expected, the regret
that I expect to have after n time steps is
I will take each action, look at the number
of times I would have played that action till
that time right, multiply it by the regret
of playing that action right. So if I played
the optimal action then the regret is 0,so
if I play some sub optimal action then I will
be adding that delta i times, the number of
times I have played that sub optimal action
i right.
So this is essentially my definition of regret
so I have now a formal way of writing down
my definition of regret, is this is clear,
any questions? Okay. so one more notation
is one thing which I yeah so one more notation
that I will have here, it is a random variable
that denotes the reward that I obtained for
playing action i at time n, some n okay some
arbitrary n, time n if I play action i right
what is the reward that I get right? since
we are assuming everything is stationary right
so the expectation of this will be, this will
tell me if people are following it or not,
so what is X i n the reward I get for playing
arm i at time n right what is the expected
value of that somebody say something.
One of you put your hand up and say something,
so that i can, its very hard for me to make
out in that murmur hand hand hand, Q star
of i, people see why since we are assuming
things are stationary this expectation is
really not going to depend on n, so then it
becomes expected reward I get for pulling
arm i which is essentially Q star i okay,
great. So anything else that I need to do
notation wise so, essentially to show this
result right, what I am going to try and show
is that, this guy is bounded and I am going
to show that that guy is bounded so what I
am going to show? We're going to show that
the expected value of T j of n or T i of n
is bounded by 8 by delta j squared ln n so,
since i multiply by another delta here to
get the regret so that will get me the first
term in the regret and some constant here
which will get me the second term in the regret.
It's not calculated at the nth stage it's
calculated by using their true values that's
Q star you do not know the values but it's
just a definition its just a quantity, that's
the expected regret that you are going to
get for playing arm i, its the expected loss
you would accrue for playing arm i.
If I had played the best arm over and over
again right, if I played the best term over
and over again I would get Q star a star if
I play arm i, I am going to get Q star i right,
so the loss i am going to get is Q star a
star minus Q star i correct, so this is what
I am denoting by delta i this is the loss
that I expect to accrue for playing arm i,
just playing with that one arm right and if
I keep playing that arm repeatedly the total
loss i am going to accrue is delta i a times
the number of times i will play i right and
I sum this over all the arms. So one of these
arms in the summation or one or more of these
arms I mean we do not know one or more of
these arms in the summation would be optimal.
And for those terms delta i will be 0, so
the regret, the contribution to the regret
will be 0 and all the other sub optimal arms
will contribute delta i to the regret. Yeah.
Because I am assuming the reward distributions
are stationary, right you remember I said
you are deciding the reward by tossing a coin
but you do not change the coin right because
you do not change the coin does not matter
when I toss the coin the probability of it
coming up heads will be the same whether I
toss it the first time or whether toss it
at the tenth time I pull the arm, the probability
of it coming heads will be the same and that
is the expectation, right so the expectation
will be the same right.
so one way to think about the this expectation
is right so, I do multiple experiments right
I do several experiments every time starting
from time 0 right, I do i do like millions
of experiments okay every time I start from
time 0 and I keep pulling arms for some number
of time steps right and then i reset my whole
system start from time 0 and pull for another
say 100 time steps or something like that
right when i do this experiments like this
in the 10th time step if I pull arm three
right so in this million experiments some
number of times I would have pulled arm three
in the 10th time step okay, then I'll take
all the rewards I saw then I'll take the average
of that right that is one way of thinking
about what this expectation means.
So now you understand right it does not matter
whether I pulled arm three at the 10th time
step or whether I pull arm three at the thousandth
time step if i take this expectation across
these million trials, it will be the same.
So that is essentially what we're saying here
okay, is it is it clear so what we are trying
to show is this right so if you are able to
show this then we are all done as long as
this constant here evaluates to 1 plus pi
squared by 3 okay our proof is all done okay.
Now we have to now go and start counting that
okay, so here things start get getting interesting
subho you want to complete the proof okay
so before I move on with the proof i will
need one more i need one more fact, so
they're on this whole set of results in probability
theory called concentration inequalities or
concentration bounds okay.
Or sometimes called large deviation bounds
okay, these are essentially results that relate
the true expectations of distributions okay,
with estimated values of those expectations
from samples not just expectations I mean
different kinds of statistics you have different
bounds you have bounds on expectations you
have bounds on variance right and so on so
forth, right so essentially the idea behind
these bounds is to kind of characterize right
so, given a certain number of samples from
which you are estimating a statistic right
the statistics in this case will for the one
that we are interested in is the expectation
right.
So we are interested in the expectation as
a statistic right, so I have some number of
samples from which I am estimating this expectation
right and I have the true expectations right
so as the number of samples increases how
quickly or how slowly does this estimation
approach my true expectation so this is something
that we want to characterize so we will talk
about one such bound which is very popular
bound which is applied all over the place
okay, so if you are going to do anything in
machine learning forget about RL anything
that has remotely shades of theoretical results
in machine learning it's a good idea to know
more about concentration bounds but at least
the least you should know about is the Chernoff
bounds or the Chernoff Hoeffding bounds.
So this is a very specialized form of the
bound I am writing right very narrow form
of the bound that i am writing specifically
for this setting that we are interested in
right the Chernoff bound is slightly more
general than what i am stating now right and
so you can look it up I mean so you can look
up I don't know your favorite online resource
right Wikipedia or whatever mathematica one
of those things right so it will give you
a more expanded bound. Okay So you can see
the setup here I am assuming that X1 to Xn
are random variables right each one with a
range 0 to 1 right, that is kind of putting
it here and if it is not in the range 0 to
1 you will have to do some kind of normalization
in the bound right, but for the time being
let's just assume it's in the range 0 to 1.
And such that the expected value of Xt right
given all the variables that came before that
is mu and then this holds for all t basically
it essentially means that all of the variables
have a mean mu, all the variables each one
independently X1 is a random variable with
mean mu in the range 0 to 1, X2 is a random
variable with mean mu in the range 0 to 1
okay. So essentially that is what we are assuming
and I am defining another random variable
which we call Sn which is essentially summing
up all the X1 to Xn and divide by n, okay
so you get that.
So what I am I trying to estimate us with
Sn, mu right I am trying to estimate the mean
mu so, one way right now let us try to make
this little concrete in our case so, that
it becomes easier for you to understand right
so X1 to Xn are random variables that are
corresponding to different times I have pulled
the same arm i right so I have pulled arm
i n times right, so every time I pull the
arm I am going to get some reward from the
range 0 to 1 right, since I am assuming it
is a stationary distribution all these rewards
will have the same mean mu, correct? And Sn
is the average right this Sn is essentially
my Q j right if you think about it so, my
Q j is like one sample of my random variable
Sn, is it clear, what I mean by saying Qj
is a sample of Sn because, Sn is a random
variable right what is Qj it is one realization
of that random variable, because I have taken
actual samples and taken the average it is
one realization of that random variable right.
And what I am going to now tell you is okay
given that i have taken n samples so, in our
case it will be Nj samples right given that
i have taken Nj samples, how can you relate
Q j with what how can I relate Q j with Q
star j okay, so given that I have taken Nj
samples which is my n here how can I relate
Q j with Q star j okay. So this is how the
hoeffding bound is applicable in our case
right so i will write down the expression
i am not going to prove it okay, so that will
get little bit more involved write down the
expression and after that we can apply it
in deriving those bonds okay.
So essentially what i have here is now the
probability that Sn is greater than or equal
to mu plus some epsilon, hmm, where did I
do a here because a is action right so I don't
want to confuse a for action with something
else yeah, this is what this is the problem
with translating on the fly okay, fine so
it should be n or n squared? Subho.. so what
does this mean the probability that my Sn
will be far away from my mu in one direction,
so mu is the true mean, Sn is the estimated
mean, the probability that Sn will be greater
than at least epsilon from mu right is lesser
than e power minus two epsilon squared n right,
so the smaller the epsilon , what happen?
Smaller the probability or larger the probability
larger the probability smaller the epsilon
larger the probability right so larger the
probability of me making an error, I mean
if I want to be really really confident then
I need more and more samples right.
If I want epsilon to be very small then n
has to be very large only then I will get
a high probability for it right what about
this it says in the other direction probability
that the estimate I make will be far away
from epsilon, basically below epsilon right
is again bounded by the same expression.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved